A Guide to the Betty L. Moss Architectural Collection, 1950-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Betty L. Moss Architectural Collection, 1950-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2008-071
268 containers; 56.75 cu. ft.
The Betty L. Moss Architectural Collection contains the architectural renderings, business correspondence/notes of Betty Moss, an architect from New Orleans, Louisiana. Types of structures included in drawings are houses, apartment buildings, condominiums, religious centers, businesses, antique shops, offices, hospitals, and centers for convalescence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Betty L. Moss Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2008.
Biographical Information
Betty Anne Lipper was born in 1921 in Houston, Texas, to Lawrence Lipper and Betty Silverman. Betty Lipper married Hartwig Moss II and had two children. Moss attended Newcomb College and Tulane University in New Orleans, Louisiana, as well as the University of Missouri School of Journalism in Colombia, Missouri, and received a bachelor's in journalism from Tulane in 1942. Moss later returned to Tulane in the 1950s and earned a bachelor's degree in Architecture in 1960. After over forty years, Moss was awarded a master's degree in architecture from Tulane in 2004. Starting her practice in her 40s, Moss continued to work for more than four decades and produced designs for many houses and small office buildings in New Orleans. An outspoken defender of building preservation and conservation, Moss ardently defended against the demolition of the Rivergate (an exhibition center) on Canal Street in New Orleans. The Rivergate was demolished; and, Moss and Abbye A. Gorin wrote a six-minute film about the structure. After Hurricane Katrina devastated New Orleans in 2005, Moss composed plans for rebuilding and safety guidelines for disaster prevention. Betty Moss died October 22, 2007.
Scope and Content
The Betty L. Moss Architectural Collection contains the drawings and business correspondence/notes of Betty L. Moss, an architect from New Orleans, Louisiana, practicing largely in the second half of the twentieth century. Structures appearing in drawings include: houses, apartment buildings, condominiums, religious centers, businesses, antique shops, offices, hospitals, and centers for convalescence. The locations of most projects center around New Orleans, Louisiana; but, some structures were designed for Texas, Mississippi, New Jersey, Tennessee, and Idaho. These drawings include projects that were constructed, as well as others that may not have been built. Projects range from plans for the design of the Moss residence made in 1950 to proposals drafted after Hurricane Katrina's devastation of New Orleans in 2005. Architectural designs on illustration board, some tinted, date from Moss's study at Tulane University. Correspondence includes letters to and from clients, professionals, and tradesmen. Interoffice notes and pages from catalogs illustrating fixtures also appear.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by architectural project. Projects appear in chronological order from their beginning.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Gorin, Abbye A. Videotape and Catalog of Work, 1995-1997. Ms97-009.
Contents List
- Single Residence for Mr. and Mrs. H. Moss, 1950-1981 (Box 1-3)
  See also Box 255 Folder 1.
- A Regional Dwelling, 1955 (Oversize 1)
- An Art Gallery, 1955 (Oversize 2)
- Residence for Mr. Esmond Phelps and A Living Porch Residence of Mr. & Mrs. Robert I. Reisfeld, 1956 [1923] (Box 4)
- A Candy Shop, 1956 (Oversize 3)
- A Methodist Church, 1956 (Oversize 4)
- Plaza Shopping--A Building for the I.L.A., 1957 (Box 5)
- A Proposed Redevelopment of 1120 Thalia Street, 1957 (Box 6)
- Hartwig Moss Insurance, 1959-2004 (Box 7-15)
  See also Box 255 Folder 2-3.
- A United States Consulate, 1960 (Oversize 5)
- An All Purpose Meeting Room, 1960 (Oversize 6)
- Temple Beth El, 1960 (Oversize 7-10)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. J. Kenneth Leithman, 1960 (Box 16)
- Lakewood South I and II, 1960-1997 (Box 17-27)
  See also Box 255 Folder 5-6.
- 411; 411-415 Royal Street, 1961-2001 (Box 28-47)
  See also Box 255 Folder 7-8.
- L'Elysee--Luxury Apartment Living, 1961 (Box 48-51)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Jack M. Weiss, 1961 (Box 52)
- Alterations to a House at 1817 Marengo Street, 1961 (Box 53)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Jack Weiss, 1961 (Box 54-55)
- National Food Store, Katz and Bestoff Drugs and Finance Company; Commercial Development--Pivach--Perino Reality Inc., 1962 (Box 56)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Maurice Feingerts, 1962-1967 (Box 57-58)
- Alterations to a House for Mr. and Mrs. Lester Shapiro, 1962 (Box 59)
- The Marguery for Urban Living, 1963 (Box 60)
- Alterations to a House for Mr. and Mrs. Adrian C. Benjamin, Jr., 1963 (Box 61)
- House for Mr. and Mrs. Paul Maloney, Jr., 1963 (Box 62)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. John Breyer, 1963 (Box 63-65)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Frank Prins, 1964 (Box 66)
- Alterations to Temple Sinai Religious School Building, 1964 (Box 67)
- An Addition to a House for Mr. and Mrs. Blake West, 1964 (Box 68)
- Moss Antiques, 1964 (Box 69)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Robert I. Reisfeld, 1964-1972 (Box 70-74)
  See also Box 255 Folder 10.
- Alterations to a House at 6201 St. Charles Ave., 1964 (Box 75)
- A House for North Pascagoula Realty Company, 1964 (Box 76-78)
- Houses for Luling, Louisiana, 1964 (Box 79)
- A House for Mr. Peter E. Newman, 1964-1965 (Box 80)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Manfred Sterner, 1964 (Box 81)
- A Pool Enclosure, 1965 (Box 82)
- An Addition to a Residence for Mr. and Mrs. Fred Kahn II, 1965 (Box 83)
- Addition to the House of Mr. and Mrs. George Marcuse, 1965 (Box 84)
- West Bank Academy (A Preliminary Design), 1965 (Box 85)
- Proposed Redevelopment of 3337 South Claiborne, 1965 (Box 86)
- A House for Dr. and Mrs. Louis Hughes, 1965 (Box 87)
- An Addition to a Residence for Mr. and Mrs. Fred Kahn II, 1965 (Box 88)
- Sara Mayo Hospital, 1965-1966 (Box 89)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. William Carter, 1965 (Box 90)
- Alterations to an Existing House for Judge and Mrs. Walter Marcus, Jr., 1966 (Box 91)
- New Threshold and Fence for Mr. and Mrs. Morris W. Newman, 1966 (Box 92)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Leonard Tubbs, Jr., 1966 (Box 93)
- Burka Job, 1966-1967 (Box 94-96)
- Proposed Four Unit Apartment Building, 1966 (Box 97)
- Alterations to a House for Mr. & Mrs. Jack M. Weiss, 1968 (Box 98)
- A House for G. Walter Loewenbaum & Mrs. Joel Simon Loewenbaum, 1968 (Box 99)
- Proposed Addition to Existing Office Building for Sam Reisfeld and Son, 1968-1970 (Box 100-104)
- A Proposed Subdivision of Lots A and B, 1969 (Box 105)
- Enclosure of First Floor Screened Porch and Playroom for Kohlmeyer, 1969 (Box 106)
- Alterations and Additions to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Milton Sbisa, 1971 (Box 107)
- Additions and Alterations to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Hartwig Moss III, 1971-1974 (Box 108)
- Alterations and Additions to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Charles Stich, 1972 (Box 109)
- A Swimming Pool and Accessory Building for Dr. and Mrs. Howard Strauss, 1972 (Box 110)
  See also Box 255 Folder 11.
- An Addition for Mr. and Mrs. Peter Moss, 1972-1976 (Box 111)
- Office Building of Robert Reisfeld, 1972-1988 (Box 112-120)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Milton Dureau, Jr., 1973-1987 (Box 121-122)
  See also Box 255 Folder 12.
- Additions and Alterations to an Existing House for Dr. and Mrs. Stuart Farber, 1973 (Box 123)
- A House for Mr. and Mrs. Lionel Lacabe, 1974 (Box 124-125)
- Griffin Project, 1975 (Box 126)
- A House for Dr. and Mrs. Alvin Alexander, 1976 (Box 127)
- Additions and Alterations to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Gerard Cooper (original and renovations), 1976 (Box 128)
- Alterations to an Existing Building for William Sabatier, 1976 (Box 129)
- 325 Royal Street, 1977-1991 (Box 130)
- St. John, 1977 (Box 131)
- Restoration of a Three Apartment Building, 1978 (Box 132-134)
- Alterations to the Cynthia Building for Mrs. Marguerite P. Keil, 1979-1981 (Box 135)
- Renovation on 1621 State Street, 1979-1986 (Box 136-138)
- Alterations to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Hartwig Moss III, 1980 (Box 139)
- Proposed Development of a Site on Versailles Blvd., 1980 (Box 140)
- Redevelopment of 730 South Pierre Street, 1980 (Box 141)
- Office Building for B&G Crane Services and Sun Erection, 1982-1984 (Box 142-148)
  See also Box 255 Folder 13.
- Donner Estates, 1985 (Box 149)
- Redevelopment of 1454 Joseph Street, 1985 (Box 150)
- Alterations to Residence F, 1986 (Box 151)
- Parking Lot Revisions for Mrs. Jon B. Strauss, 1986 (Box 152)
- Alterations to 6319 Story St., 1986 (Box 153)
- Carport Enclosure at 222 Hector Avenue, 1986 (Box 154)
  See also Box 255 Folder 14.
- Additions and Alterations to 1636 Valence Street, 1987 (Box 155-156)
- A House for Mildred G. Tobias, 1987 (Box 157)
- Greengates Revised, 1987 (Box 158)
  See also Box 255 Folder 15.
- Alterations to 313 Royal Street, 1988 (Box 159)
- Part Seventh Floor Plan Park VII Apartments, 1988 (Box 160)
- Antique Furniture Storage Building for Mrs. Jon Strauss, 1989 (Box 161)
- Variations on a House for a 30'x120' Interior, 1989 (Box 162)
- Alterations to an Existing House for Mr. and Mrs. Robert Rosenberg, 1989 (Box 163)
  See also Box 255 Folder 16.
- Burrow Project-a Driveway and Bath, 1990-1994 (Box 164)
  See also Box 255 Folder 17.
- Cola Job, 1991-2000 (Box 165)
  See also Box 255 Folder 18.
- Renovation of 4602-4604 Constance Street, 1992 (Box 166)
- Combination of K & L, Fourth Floor, 2100 St. Charles Ave, 1992 (Box 167)
- Garfield Street Job, 1992 (Box 168)
- Restoration of 3012-3014 Bienville Street, 1993-1994 (Box 169)
  See also Box 255 Folder 19.
- Lambeth House, 1993-1994, See also Box 255 Folder 20. (Box 170-171)
- Proposed Housing for Indigent Mothers with AIDS with Children with AIDS, 1993 (Box 172)
- Adaptive Re-use of Rivergate as the Land-based Gambling Casino in New Orleans, 1994 (Box 173)
- Proposed Adaptive Re-Use of 3000 Magazine as a Facility for Persons with AIDS, Arrested Tuberculosis and Related Problems, 1994 (Box 174)
- Renovation of 7614 Sycamore, 1994 (Box 175)
- Alterations to an Existing House for Mrs. Jon B. Strauss, 1995 (Box 176)
  See also Box 255 Folder 21.
- Preliminary Schematic Redevelopment of 213-215 Alonzo Street, 1994 (Box 177)
  See also Box 255 Folder 22.
- 2200 St. Charles Ave. Condominium, 1995-2002 (Box 178-180)
- Alterations to Fairway Drive Residence, 1997-2000 (Box 181)
  See also Box 255 Folder 23.
- A House for Shawn Doyle, 1998 (Box 182-183)
  See also Box 255 Folder 24.
- Rearrangements of 1 Apartment, 1999 (Box 184)
  See also Box 255 Folder 25.
- Rearrangements to 4M: The Carol Condominium, 1991 (Box 185)
  See also Box 255 Folder 26.
- A House for Anne and Lou Zenowich, 1999-2000 (Box 186-194)
  See also Box 255 Folder 27.
- Rearrangements to an Apartment for Mr. and Mrs. Fred Jellin, 2001 (Box 195)
  See also Box 255 Folder 28.
- A Plan for West Village, 2004-2005 (Box 196-201)
  See also Box 255 Folder 29.
- A Swinging Gate for Mr. and Mrs. Morris Newman, 2005 (Box 202)
- Preliminary Plan for Moss Family LLC, 2005 (Box 203)
- A Block for New Orleans, 2005 (Box 204-208)
  See also Box 255 Folder 30-31.
- A House for 2525 Deers Street, 2006 (Box 209-210)
- 231 Royal Street, 2006 (Box 211)
- A House for Joseph Garcia, 2006 (Box 212)
- Alterations and Additions to 965 Nashville Ave., n.d. (Box 213-214)
- Renovation of 305 Royal Street, n.d. (Box 215-216)
- Selma Moss, Inc., n.d. (Box 217-218)
- House for Mr. and Mrs. Cleven J. Daigle, n.d. (Box 219)
- A Residence for Mr. and Mrs. Lester A. Levy, n.d. (Box 220)
- W. G. Moses Residence, n.d. (Box 221-222)
- A House for Lakewood Builders, Inc., n.d. (Box 223)
- Repairs to 5127 Laurel Street, n.d. (Box 224)
- Building on Carrollton Avenue and Zimple Street, n.d. (Box 225)
- Linda Vista, n.d. (Box 226)
- Job on the Intersection of Montegut and Chartres Street, n.d. (Box 227)
  See also Box 255 Folder 32.
- 78-80 Newcomb Blvd., n.d. (Box 228)
- 12-A and 12-b Austerlitz Street, n.d. (Box 229)
- Diagram of City Blocks, n.d. (Box 230)
- 4118 Constance Street, n.d. (Box 231)
- Untitled Multi-drawing Projects, n.d. (Box 232-248)
- Untitled Single Drawings, n.d. (Box 249-254, Oversize 11-12)
- Note Accompanying Plans for Moss Residence, n.d. (Box-folder 255:1)
- Safety Code Materials for Hartwig Moss Insurance, n.d. (Box-folder 255:2)
- Letters to Hartwig Moss Insurance, 1993, 2004 (Box-folder 255:3)
- Note from the Louisiana Landmarks Society, 1960 (Box-folder 255:4)
- 5574 Jacquelyn Court Project, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 255:5)
- "Event Notice" (Originally with Jacquelyn Court Plans), 1997 (Box-folder 255:6)
- Materials Concerning 411 Royal Street, 1992 (Box-folder 255:7)
- Sketch of 411-413 Royal Street, n.d. (Box-folder 255:8)
- Certificate of Insurance for Weiss Project, 1962 (Box-folder 255:9)
- Microfilm of Reisfeld Project, n.d. (Box-folder 255:10)
- Materials Accompanying Strauss Project, 1959, 1971 (Box-folder 255:11)
- Letter to Mr. and Mrs. Milton Dureau, 1987 (Box-folder 255:12)
- Materials for B&G Crane Services Project, 1983 (Box-folder 255:13)
- Letter and Survey Sent to Zoning and Appeals Board for Stone Project, 1986 (Box-folder 255:14)
- Envelope with Measurements [Originally with Greengates Revised], n.d. (Box-folder 255:15)
- Envelope with Handwritten Specifications and Sketches, n.d. (Box-folder 255:16)
- Specifications for Burrow Driveway, c. 1990-1991 (Box-folder 255:17)
- Supporting Materials for Cola Job, 2000 (Box-folder 255:18)
- Supporting Materials for the Associated Catholic Charities Project, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 255:19)
- Letter Concerning the Proposed Development of Lambeth House, 1994 (Box-folder 255:20)
- Specifications for Strauss Project, n.d. (Box-folder 255:21)
- Letters and Specifications for 213-215 Alonzo Street, 1994 (Box-folder 255:22)
- Survey of 204 Fairway Drive, 1994 (Box-folder 255:23)
- Materials Concerning Doyle Project, 1998 (Box-folder 255:24)
- Plumbing Specifications for the "Rearrangements of One Apartment," n.d. (Box-folder 255:25)
- Scribbling Concerning 4M: The Carol Condominium, n.d. (Box-folder 255:26)
- Request Form Concerning Zenowich Project, 2001 (Box-folder 255:27)
- Schedule of Openings, Specifications, and Drawings for "Rearrangements to an Apartment," n.d. (Box-folder 255:28)
- Letter Concerning Hummel Project, 2005 (Box-folder 255:29)
- Letter "To Whom it May Concern," 2005 (Box-folder 255:30)
- Letter to the Honorable Barney Frank, 2007 (Box-folder 255:31)
- Directions to "Keep it Simple," n.d. (Box-folder 255:32)
- Mathematical Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 255:33)
- Untitled Drawings and Catalog Pages, n.d. (Box-folder 255:34)
- Art Print, n.d. (Box 256)